Grand Central Moderns Records
Grand Central Moderns Records
1947-1967
Grand Central Moderns.
3 linear ft.
The Grand Central Moderns, under the direction of Colette Roberts, was a "non-profit organization dealing in Modern American Art," a branch of the "long-established institution known as Grand Central Art Galleries." Original material pertaining to group and solo exhibitions held at Grand Central Moderns as well as an assortment of personal papers of Colette Roberts. Gallery material consists of clippings, correspondence, exhibition catalogs, photographs, and press releases relating to seventy-nine artists represented by the Gallery as well as several group exhibitions. The Colette Roberts material contains correspondence, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, writings, and memorabilia.
146325
Biographical History
The Grand Central Moderns was the modern art division of the Grand Central Art Galleries, established in 1922 by director Erwin S. Barrie. The gallery was located in Manhattan's Grand Central Terminal and was founded as a non-profit organization designed to support American artists.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Grand Central Moderns Records collection contains material from the Grand Central Moderns art gallery in New York City from approximately 1951 through 1965 while under the curatorial direction of Colette Roberts. The Gallery material consists mainly of correspondence relatating to various artists, but also includes clippings, exhibition catalogs, photographs, and press releases. Seventy-nine artists are represented within the collection, among them Byron Browne, Lamar Dodd, Jennett Lam, and Louise Nevelson. The Colette Roberts material contains clippings, correspondence, memorabilia, newsletters, photographs of the work of various artists, and writings as well as exhibition catalogs and press releases from other galleries and museums.
Arrangement of the Collection
Gallery material (Boxes 1-3) begins with correspondence, which is sorted alphabetically by subject or personal name. Printed material (Box 3) consists of clippings, exhibition catalogs/announcements, newsletters, and press releases, in that order.
Collete Roberts papers (Box 3) starts with correspondence and is followed by photographs, printed material, writings, and memorabilia. Correspondence is ordered by date. The photographs are of art work and are arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the artist. Printed material includes clippings, exhibition catalogs/announcements, museum guide-books, press releases, and publicity, all ordered by date. Writings and memorabilia are also arranged by date where applicable.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Art -- Painters; Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Sculptors; Roberts, Colette, 1910-1971.; Grand Central Moderns -- Archives.; Art, Exhibitions.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Art galleries, Commercial -- United States.; Artists -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women art critics -- United States.; Women art historians -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Women painters -- United States.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Announcements.; Bulletins.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Guidebooks.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Art critics.; Art historians.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.; Art galleries.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Colette Roberts, director.
Inventory
- Gallery
  - Correspondence - subject files
    - Activities (General), 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Adler, Samuel (Box 1)
    - "An Architects's Choice", May 10-June 8, 1954; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Asher, Elise (Box 1)
    - Banks, Virginia, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Beattie, George (Box 1)
    - Betsberg, Ernestine (Box 1)
    - Boxer, Stanley (Box 1)
    - Browne, Byron, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Campbell, Kenneth (Box 1)
    - Candell, Victor, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Carlson, Edith (Box 1)
    - Chadbourn, Alfred (Box 1)
    - Cheney, Lewis (Box 1)
    - Conway, Fred (Box 1)
    - Cook, Howard, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Corcos, Lucille (Box 1)
    - Cress, George (Box 1)
    - Day, Worden (Box 1)
    - De Martini, Joseph (Box 1)
    - Dodd, Lamar (Box 1)
    - Durfee, Hazard (Box 1)
    - Elliott, Ronnie (Box 1)
    - Ellis, Dean (Box 1)
    - England, Paul (Box 1)
    - "An Exchange Exhibition, Paris - New York", Oct 5-24, 1953; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Fine, Albert (Box 1)
    - Flettrich, Leonard (Box 1)
    - Ford, Gigi (Box 1)
    - "4 Murals", Nov 1-18, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Freborg, Stan (Box 1)
    - Galantiere, Nancy (Box 2)
    - Geoffrey, J. Iqbal, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Golbin, Andree (Box 2)
    - Goldring, Milton, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Gonzalez, Xavier (Box 2)
    - Grant, James (Box 2)
    - "Guest Sculptors", Jan 3-27, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Hare, Channing (Box 2)
    - Hasen, Burton, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Hebald, Milton (Box 2)
    - Hensel, Hopkins (Box 2)
    - Houser, Jim (Box 2)
    - "The Island", Oct 13-Nov 8, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Kearl, Stanley Brandon (Box 2)
    - Lam, Jennett (Box 2)
    - Lethem, Richard (Box 2)
    - Livitan, Israel (Box 2)
    - Lund, David (Box 2)
    - Macdonald, Herbert (Box 2)
    - Madrigal, August (Box 2)
    - Manso, Leo (Box 2)
    - Marren, Janet (Box 2)
    - Mikus, Eleanore (Box 2)
    - Miyashita, Tad (Box 2)
    - Moffitt, Elizabeth (Box 2)
    - Morrison, George, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Moy, Seong, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Narotzky, Norman (Box 2)
    - Nevelson, Louise (Box 2)
    - "New York", Summer 1952 (Box 2)
    - Niewald, Wilbur (Box 2)
    - Osver, Arthur, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Outlook 1955", Jan 27-Feb 17, 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Outlook 1956", Apr 28-May 12, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Parsons, Betty (Box 2)
    - Preminger, Mary Gardner (Box 2)
    - Ray, Rudolf (Box 2)
    - Reid, Robert (Box 2)
    - Robus, Hugo (Box 2)
    - Roth, Jack (Box 2)
    - Rowan, Herman (Box 2)
    - Ruben, Richard (Box 2)
    - Russo, Alexander (Box 2)
    - Shahly, Jehan (Box 2)
    - Simon, Sidney (Box 2)
    - Steffen, Bernard (Box 2)
    - Stoltenberg, Donald (Box 2)
    - Taplitz (Box 3)
    - Thompson, William (Box 3)
    - Trotter, McKie (Box 3)
    - Twiggs, Russell (Box 3)
    - Twirbutt, Josef (Box 3)
    - Wald, Sylvia (Box 3)
    - Watts, Robert (Box 3)
    - Wilson, Sybil (Box 3)
    - Woods, Conrad (Box 3)
    - Zuka (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1951-1961; undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs/announcements (miscellaneous), 1952-1961; undated (Box 3)
    - Newsletters, 1953-1965 (Box 3)
    - Press releases, 1951-1960; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
- Collette Roberts
  - Correspondence - subject file
    - Miscellany, 1953; 1957-1964,; undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Artwork, By artist A-Z, unknown; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1950-1964; undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibition catalogs/announcements (miscellaneous), 1947; 1954-1965,; undated; 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Museum guide-books
      - The Art Gallery, Oct 1962-Apr 1967; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - The New York Arts Calendar, May 1964; Oct-Dec 1964 (Box 3)
    - Press releases (miscellaneous), 1957-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Publicity (personal), undated (Box 3)
  - Writings
    - Miscellany, 1953-1963; undated (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia
    - Course material, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellany, 1961-1965; undated (Box 3)